We are now going to turn our attention to wide area networks, also known as WANs. WANs are networks that cover multiple geographical areas and are usually a collection of LANs.
For example, a company could have its corporate headquarters in one location and have satellite offices in multiple locations, each with its own LAN.
And often, leased lines are used to connect these networks. A leased line is a dedicated connection from one location to another.
There are several types of leased lines you need to know about for the exam, and the next few topics will go into details on those types of leased lines.
One type of line that is not a leased line is a dial-up line. Though pretty rare, dial-up is still the only means of getting to the outside world for some users.
In order to utilize a dial-up connection, a phone line and a server which accepts dial-up connections is needed. Dial-up connections are very, very slow by today's standards.
The top advertised speed is 56 Kbps, but in reality, 38 Kbps or so is about as fast of a connection as one can expect through dial-up connections.
One of the first advancements from dial-up is that of Integrated Services Digital Network, or ISDN for short. There are two types of ISDN connections.
Basic Rate ISDN, or BRI, this uses two 64 Kbps channels for a total speed of 128 Kbps, more than double that of a dial-up connection. There's also Primary Rate ISDN, or PRI.
This uses twenty-three 64 Kbps channels for a total speed of 1.536 Mbps. PRI runs on a T1 circuit line. T-lines will be covered shortly.